Inventory of the Ivy House Restaurant Records 1906-1985
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Ivy House Restaurant Records 1906-1985 1948-1960
Special Collections Research Center
01/Mss. Acc. 2007.51
3.00
The records of the Ivy House Restaurant in Williamsburg, Virginia include business records, guest registers, customer and business correspondence, legal documents, and a variety of ephemera from the local business including menus. This mid-20th century collection documents the history of this restaurant during a time when Williamsburg was going through changes and growth in the tourism industry.
The Ivy House Restaurant (Williamsburg, VA); Rutledge, David; Rutledge, Emily arrangement
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Box 4 contains confidential information pertaining to employees and is closed to researchers until 2035. All other portions of the collection are open to researchers.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Special Collections Research Center from The Ivy House Restaurant on 00/00/2000.
Historical Note
The Ivy House was opened in 1948 by David and Emily Rutledge, alumni of the College of William and Mary. Though the restaurant originally served three meals a day, it quickly became a breakfast only restaurant with the success of the Rutledge's "astronomical" pancakes. Further information about this individual or organization may be available in the Special Collections Research Center Wiki: http://scrc.swem.wm.edu/wiki/index.php/The Ivy House Restaurant (Williamsburg, VA).
Scope and Contents
The records of the Ivy House Restaurant in Williamsburg, Virginia include business records, guest registers, customer and business correspondence, legal documents, and a variety of ephemera from the local business including menus. This mid-20th century collection documents the history of this restaurant during a time when Williamsburg was going through changes and growth in the tourism industry.
Arrangement of Materials
This collection is arranged by series: Series 1: Correspondence; Series 2: Administrative Records.
Additional Information
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence; Deeds; Financial records; Menus; Printed ephemera
Topical Term:
Account books.; Cookery--Virginia--Williamsburg.; Guestbooks; Paper money.; Restaurants--Virginia--Williamsburg.; Williamsburg (Va.)--History.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Correspondence, 1939-1973; id4905
  - id72461 (Box 1)
    - Addresses of Astrononomical Pancake Club Members, circa 1950-1959; id72463 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Notes from Children, Circa 1954; id72464 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Complaints about the Ivy House, 1951-1954; id72465 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Addressed Post Cards, 1955-1969; id72466 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, circa 1950-1959; id72467 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence from Alabama, 1948-1953; id72468 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence from Alaska, 1956; id72469 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence from Arizona, 1956; id72470 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence from California, 1951-1959; id72472 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence from Connecticut, 1950-1959; id72473 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence from Florida, 1949-1960; id72474 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence from Georgia, 1952-1958; id72475 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence from Illinois, 1949-1959; id72476 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence from Indiana, 1949-1957; id72477 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence from Kansas, 1954; id72478 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence from Kentucky, 1955, 1957; id72479 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence from Louisiana, 1951-1959; id72480 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence with Maine, 1949, 1957; id72481 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence from Maryland, 1951-1960; id72482 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence from Massachusetts, 1951-1960; id72483 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence from Michigan, 1949-1959; id72484 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence from Minnesota, 1953-1956; id72485 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence from Missouri, 1951-1957; id72486 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence from Nebraska, 1962; id72487 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence from New Hampshire, 1951-1959; id72488 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence from New Jersey, 1949-1961; id72489 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence from New York, 1948-1963; id72490 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Correspondance from North Carolina, 1951-1959; id72492 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence from Ohio, 1949-1959; id72494 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence from Oklahoma, 1951-1955; id72499 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence from Oregon, 1951-1954; id72501 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence from Rhode Island, 1950, 1958; id72574 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence from South Carolina, 1952-1959; id72575 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Correspondance from Tennesse, 1954-1960; id72576 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence from Texas, 1951-1959; id72577 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Correspondance From Virginia, 1949-1959; id72579 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence from Washington D.C., circa 1950-1959; id72580 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Correspondence from Washington State, 1958; id72582 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence from West Virginia, circa 1950-1959; id72583 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence from Wisconsin, 1956; id72584 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Correspondence from Canada, 1950-1961; id72586 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Correspondence from Europe, 1955-1958; id72589 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Correspondence from the Carribean and Chile, 1950-1961; id72588 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Correspondance From Lebanon, circa 1950-1959; id72590 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Correspondance with AAA, 1950; id72591 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Correspondance with Ford Motor Company, circa 1950-1959; id72593 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Correspondance with Gourmet Magazine, 1950-1953; id72594 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Correspondance with Duncan Hines, 1949-1951; id72595 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Business Correspondance, 1952-1967; id72596 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Correspondence with Lawry's Seasoned Salt, undated; id72598 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Letter from Jeanne Etheridge to Emily Rutledge, 1973; id72599 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Postcard from the New York Worlds Fair, 1939; id72601 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Artifacts sent to the Ivy House from Canada, China, and Mexico, undated; id72602 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Hand Drawn Pictures, 1956; id72603 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Cards and Addresses from Rutledges, Circa 1950; id72604 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Unaddressed Postcards, Circa 1950; id72605 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Christmas Cards, Circa 1950; id72844 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Christmas Cards, Circa 1950; id72845 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Christmas Cards, Circa 1950; id72846 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Christmas Cards, Circa 1950; id72847 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Christmas Cards, Circa 1950; id72848 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - id72910 (Box 3)
    - Placemat Messages, 1951-1957; id72911 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence from Pennsylvania, undated; id72913 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Texas Play Money and Photo, undated; id72995 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Photographs, undated; id72996 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Newspaper Articles, undated; id72997 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Postcards and Correspondence, undated; id72999 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Postcards, undated; id73000 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Administrative Records, 1906-1985; id4906
  - id72849 (Box 2)
    - Tax Information for Employers, Circa 1960; id72850 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Trademark Papers and Lease Agreement, 1954-1960; id72851 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Bill of Sale of the Ivy House, 1948; id72852 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Proof of Ownership of 1336 Richmond Road, 1948; id72854 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Lease, 1953; id72855 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Option Agreement, 1960; id72858 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Deed of Trust for Ivy House, 1961; id72866 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Deeds and Mortgages from Atlantic County, New Jersey, 1908-1935; id72870 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Non-Negotiable Warehouse Reciept, 1931; id72880 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Reciepts for Copies of Documents, Atlantic County, New Jersey, 1934; id72891 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Homemakers Club Program, 1964; id72892 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - The Writers Guide; Secrets of Plot Building Rules for Preparing Manuscript, 1927; id72894 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Newspaper Clippings about the Ivy House, 1949-1959; id72895 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Pioneer Magazine, Winter Issue, 1951; id72896 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Unknown Business Cards and Addresses, 1953-1960; id72897 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Business Cards A-F, Circa 1950; id72898 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Business Cards G-K, Circa 1950; id72899 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Business Cards L-R, Circa 1950; id72900 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Business Cards S-Z, Circa 1950; id72901 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - id73014 (Box 3)
    - Guest Register, 1952; id73001 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Guest Register, 1940; id73002 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Guest Register, 1949-1951; id73003 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Guest Register, 1951-1952; id73005 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Guest Register, 1953; id73006 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Guest Register, 1954; id73007 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Guest Register, 1955; id73008 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Guest Register, 1957; id73010 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Guest Register, 1958; id73011 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Guest Register, 1959; id73012 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Guest Register, 1960; id73013 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Waiter Instructions and Mailing List, undated; id73016 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Specialty Menus, undated; id73017 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Advertisements, circa 1950-1959; id75042 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - id73024 (Box 4)
    - Financial Ledger, 1957-1958; id73025 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Financial Ledger, 1950-1952; id73026 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Financial Ledger, 1949-1960; id73027 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Financial Ledger, 1953-1954; id73029 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Financial Ledger, 1953-1954; id73030 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Financial Ledger, 1951-1952; id73032 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Gazette Common Glory Supplement, id74986
  - Menus, undated; id75016